Guide to the Morris and Dorothy Margolin Film Collection, 1947-1982 and undated RL.10157
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Morris and Dorothy Margolin film collection
1947-1982 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Margolin, Morris, 1908-1990
RL.10157
10.5 Linear Feet
The Morris and Dorothy Margolin film collection dates from 1947 to 1982 and includes twenty-five 16mm and seven Super 8 motion picture films created by Morris Margolin, chiefly documenting Morris and Dorothy's international travels. The films include footage from Pakistan, Bulgaria, Ethiopia, and Kenya -- rare destinations for Western travelers in the 1950s, 1960s, and 1970s. Highlights include an abundance of images of the Soviet Union and Israel, and images of Capetown documenting the apartheid years. All of the films are color, and a few include sound elements such as narration, music, or even sound effects. The collection also includes a handful of home movies that document family trips and events such as graduations and birthdays, and one film that appears to be a professionally produced documentary about the Soviet Union. The films are complemented by over 4,000 color slides of still images taken during their travels. The collection, arranged chronologically, also includes Digital Betacam preservation tapes, DVD masters and DVD use copies.
Approx. 4850 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research and digital viewing copies are also available through this collection guide. Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Morris and Dorothy Margolin film collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006 and 2011.
Biographical Note
Born on July 28, 1908 in Brooklyn, New York, Morris Margolin spent most of his life in the New York metropolitan area. He graduated from New York University (NYU) in 1926 and taught accounting at Far Rockaway High School in Queens, New York from 1933 to 1940. Morris was the founding partner of Margolin, Winer & Evans, an accounting firm established in Jamaica, New York, in 1946 that later moved to Garden City, Long Island. He was also a charter member and former president of the Jamaica, Queens, chapter of B'nai B'rith, a global Jewish community service organization.
In 1936, Morris married Dorothy Safran. Dorothy was born to Polish parents in Budapest, Hungary, on July 28, 1911. Her family emmigrated to the United States in 1913 and settled in New York City. Dorothy graduated from NYU, where she studied Spanish language and culture, and also did graduate work. Dorothy was a lover of the arts and an active member of Women Strike for Peace. The couple had two daughters: Elaine, born in 1940, and Linda, born in 1944.
Morris was an amateur filmmaker, photography enthusiast, and classical music aficionado. The Margolins were avid travelers, taking an extensive series of international trips. Morris documented their travels through his photography and filmmaking and then shared his films with fellow members of the Metropolitan Film Club in Manhattan and at B'nai B'rith functions. The couple also hosted screenings in their home for friends and family.
Morris retired in 1970, and the Margolins soon moved to Palm Beach, Florida, where Morris continued to share his films and photos with new friends. Morris passed away in 1990, Dorothy in 2007.
Collection Overview
The Morris and Dorothy Margolin Film Collection includes 32 home movies that capture the Margolins' travels between 1947 and 1976. Destinations represented in the collection include Austria, Belgium, Bulgaria, Canada, Denmark, England, Ethiopia, France, Germany, Greece, Hawaii, Hong Kong, Hungary, Israel, Italy, Japan, Jamaica, Kenya, Majorca, Monaco, Morocco, Norway, Pakistan, Portugal, Puerto Rico, Romania, Scotland, South Africa, the Soviet Union, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland, Tanzania, Thailand, Turkey, and Yugoslavia. All of the films are in color, and a few include sound.
Also included is a handful of home movies that document family trips and events such as graduations and birthdays, and one film that appears to be a professionally produced documentary about the Soviet Union acquired by the Margolins during their travels.
Particularly notable is the adventurous nature of many of the countries visited, such as the Soviet Union, Pakistan, Bulgaria, Ethiopia, and Kenya -- rare destinations for Western travelers in the 1950s, 1960s, and 1970s. The films are also noteworthy because Morris often trained his camera on his surroundings, recording everyday life as well as architectural and geographical features of the countries he visited. His wife Dorothy also makes frequent appearances in the films.
The films are complemented by over 4,000 color slides taken in most of these same countries from 1959 to 1982. Of particular interest are images from the former Soviet Union and Israel, both from the mid-1960s, images of South Africa during apartheid, as well as early images of France, Italy, and Thailand.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement and technical notes
The films are arranged chronologically and includes Super 8mm and 16mm reversal originals as well as Digital Betacam preservation tape masters and DVD masters. DVD use copies of each film are available to researchers. All of the films in the collection are in color. Many are silent, but some include sound elements such as voiceover narration, music, and even sound effects.
Film titles were taken directly from original labels and typically give an overview of destinations visisted on a particular trip. For most films, a preliminary or detailed shot list is included in the collection guide. These provide more information on specific cities and sites visited. Reel numbers were assigned by archivists during processing; they generally reflect order of accession.
The slides are also arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by country.
Scotland -- Description and travel; South Africa -- Description and travel; Spain -- Description and travel; Sweden -- Description and travel; Pakistan -- Description and travel; Portugal -- Description and travel; Puerto Rico -- Description and travel; Romania -- Description and travel; United States -- Description and travel; Soviet Union -- Description and travel; Yugoslavia -- Description and travel; Switzerland -- Description and travel; Tanzania -- Description and travel; Thailand -- Description and travel; Turkey -- Description and travel; Home movies; Audiovisual materials; Greece -- Description and travel; Germany -- Description and travel; Hong Kong (China) -- Description and travel; Hawaii -- Description and travel; Israel -- Description and travel; Hungary -- Description and travel; Italy -- Description and travel; Tourism -- Pictorial works; 16mm; Canada -- Description and travel; International travel -- Pictorial works; England -- Description and travel; Denmark -- Description and travel; France -- Description and travel; Ethiopia -- Description and travel; Belgium -- Description and travel; Austria -- Description and travel; Reversal film; Color films (visual works); Norway -- Description and travel; Morocco -- Description and travel; Monaco -- Description and travel; Majorca (Spain) -- Description and travel; Kenya -- Description and travel; Jamaica -- Description and travel; Japan -- Description and travel; Bulgaria -- Description and travel; Color slides; Europe -- Description and travel -- 19th century; 16mm; Super 8; Travelogs; Motion pictures (visual works); Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Margolin family; Margolin, Dorothy; Metropolitan Film Club
- Films, 1947-1976; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Shotlists were created by Rubenstein Library staff for a number of the films. Contact the Rubenstein Library for further information.
  - Happy Days Camp Life, 1947, 1; 12.04 minutes
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 12.04 minutes (Box 4, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0001)
  - France, Belgium, Switzerland, Austria, Italy, 1953, 2; 25.37 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0002 France, Belgium, Switzerland, Austria, Italy, 1953 Reversal original, 16mm, sound, color 25.37 minutes
    Includes narration and music.
    • title card: "Characters? - And How - Dorothy Frances Sam" • map of Europe with title "Vagabonds 1953" • deck of ocean liner • interiors of ship • ship's crew working • life preserver labeled: "Ile de France / Le Havre" • man smoking cigar; interiors of ship • views of the ocean • deck of the ocean liner, Dorothy walks toward camera, poses, waves • interior of the ship, Dorothy walks toward camera • interior of the ship, Morris and Dorothy walk toward camera • three men (friends of the Margolins?) on deck of the ship • Dorothy and friend relax in lounge chairs on ship deck • Dorothy looks out at the ocean, walks to group and socializes on ship deck • Dorothy, friend and Morris walk down stairs to deck and toward the camera • Morris and Dorothy walk around on ship deck, up a set of stairs • Morris poses near railing, ocean behind him; smokes a cigarette • Morris walks around on deck with a friend, talking • Dorothy and others on lounge chairs • Dorothy poses near railing, walks around on deck • street scenes in Paris, includes shots of Dorothy walking around • sign: "Grand Marnier / La Maison du Café" • street scenes in Paris • Dorothy and friends turn around and wave at camera • building: Louvre; Dorothy and friends nearby • Arc de Triomphe and environs • man (Sam Rosenberg?) walks toward camera, wiping his face, camera in hand • woman (Frances?) walks across the frame • "former Russian countess" tour guide in horse-drawn carriage • scooter travels down narrow Parisian? street • Morris and Dorothy walk into the frame, cross street • Dorothy on roadside in rural Switzerland • Alps, Dorothy waves from below, fellow travelers nearby • mountain peaks, Rhone Glacier • scenic shots of the Alps, some with Dorothy • Dorothy and others stand near "former Hotel Grand Majestic Mattenhoffer" • street scenes of Interlaken, Switzerland • group climbs into car • snowcapped Jungfrau • street scenes of Innsbruck, Austria • Innsbruck railroad station • bombed out building near Innsbruck railroad station, Dorothy nearby • couple walks by wearing traditional Austrian clothing • jeep, American GIs? • more bombed out buildings • Dorothy walks toward camera, Tirol/Tyrol? Hotel in background • Dorothy and Frances? in horse-drawn carriage • exteriors of Palace of Franz Joseph • bombed out buildings, underexposed and dark • scenery, and horse, as shot from horse-drawn carriage • Dorothy at mountainside restaurant, aerial view of Innsbruck • visit to Vatican, includes Vatican Museum, Cathedral of St. Peter and St. Peter's Square • Mussolini's balcony • Monument to King Victor Emmanuel and Tomb of the Unknown Soldier in Rome • Dorothy outside castle in Bruges, Belgium • Manneken Pis in Brussels, Belgium • lacemaker tatting near store: Real Belgian Lace • Manneken Pis • city square in Belgium • Dorothy asks police men for directions • flowers market on the square • life preserver • return trip on Steamship Independence • close up: New York • Dorothy and others relaxing on the ship deck • narration snippet: "Enjoy yourself, honey. Just a couple of more days to go. You can still be a lady. And then back to scrubbing floors, scrubbing ears, and sending the kids off to school. Won't be long now, honey. Your holiday is over." • empty lounge chairs on deck • shots of the coastline of the Azores, Dorothy on deck • Dorothy walks to ship deck with binoculars, looks at Azores • more scenic shots of the Azores • Dorothy, friends and others lounge on ship deck • kids splash around in deck pool • aerial shot of deck pool • woman in bikini and high heels plays with a dog • ship arrives in New York, passes Statue of Liberty in distance • Dorothy poses with New York City skyline in the background • Morris ends narration with: "The bar is now open. You may continue drinking."
    - Reversal original, 16mm, sound, color, 25.37 minutes (Box 1, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0002)
  - French Riviera, Israel, 1953, 3; 19.22 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0003 French Riviera, Israel, 1953 Reversal original, 16mm, sound, color 19.22 minutes
    • Israeli flag flying on top of a tower • plane parked on tarmac in "the new state of Israel" • sign: "Nazareth Souvenir Shop" • street scenes, architecture • sign: "Synagogue" • children playing in the streets • people ride donkeys through town • town watering hole • children ham it up for the camera • "typical Arab home" • locals pass by on mules • goats grazing in field • Sea of Galilee / Lake Tiberias and surrounding landscape • kibbutz • village • street scenes in Safed • Israeli soldiers • catacombs • Israel soldiers running along road • sign in Hebrew • Mount Herzl • grave of Theodor Herzl • Jerusalem from a distance • children approach driver's side of car, as captured from passenger seat • landscapes • sign: "Haifa-Tel Aviv Road" • scenes of Israeli soldiers, including women • Israeli children playing, doing hand stands • man on donkey in middle of the road • in-transit camps, settlements for European refugees • fortress in upper Galilee • countryside, Hula Swamp area • Morris and friend? inside fortress • travel along newly constructed highways, captured from inside the car • sign: "Danger-Frontier Ahead-No Passage (multiple languages)" • cattle walk along the road • sign: "Upper Galilee Regional Council" • scenes at a kibbutz • ruins of Arab city • scenes of the Negev desert and Bedouin settlements • Morris on a camel ride • more scenes of the Negev desert and Bedouin settlements • Morris stands next to tri-directional sign • Weizmann Institute of Science in Rehovot, Israel • landscapes, including olive trees • people along roadside, captured from inside the car • Morris stands next to tri-directional sign, ruins of Arab village in the background • entering Jerusalem by car • exteriors of King David Hotel • path to Mt. Zion • sign: "B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundation at the Hebrew University" • grounds of Hebrew University • airplane on tarmac • roulette wheel, stacks of coins • title card: "Why 50 Million Frenchies Can't Be Wrong" • Carlton Hotel in Cannes, France • beach scenes • Morris poses with woman on the beach • friends? of Morris interact with the same woman • swimming pool overlooking the Mediterranean • life preserver: Eden Roc / Cap of Antibes • Dorothy sitting on Eden Roc • person dives into Mediterranean • Dorothy and Frances rinse off • swimmer climbs up hanging ladder from water • fireworks
    - Reversal original, 16mm, sound, color, 19.22 minutes (Box 1, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0003)
  - Elaine's Graduation P.S. 178 / Greenbrier / Washington / Linda's Birthday / Phillips Castle, Rip Van Winkle, Tarrytown, 1953, 4; 9.18 minutes
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 9.18 minutes (Box 4, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0004)
  - Camp Life, 1954, 5; 4.55 minutes
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 4.55 minutes (Box 4, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0005)
  - Liberté (ship), England, Scotland, 1955, 6; 37.34 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0006 Liberté, England, Scotland, 1955 Reversal original, 16mm, sound, color 37.34 minutes
    • blending of people waving from a pier and the Liberté docked in the harbor • Liberté: Ocean Liner from New York City to London. On June 29, 1955 • ocean liner Liberté seen from port • crowds and Margolin family seeing them off at pier. people on deck of Liberté • view of New York City skyline, Statue of Liberty, and other boats taken from ship • fire safety drill • deck tennis • crew working on ship • transfer from Liberté to smaller boat to go to Plymouth, England • London • Grovener House hotel • street scenes • men in kilts • shops • traffic • double decker bus • Piccadilly Circus • theatre district • 10 Downing Street • school children • Westminster Abbey • Houses of Parliament • Big Ben (in scaffolding) • River Thames • Scotland Yard • St. Paul's Cathedral • bombed out rubble from World War II • New Bond Street • Tower of London • Buckingham Palace • changing of the guard • Princess Anne looking out of Buckingham Palace window • small town outside of London • street scenes • outdoor market • Oxford • street scenes • colleges • High Street • students • Broad Street • bicycles • Stratford-Upon-Avon • Ann Hathaway Cottage • street scenes • Warwick Castle • punting • Edinburgh, Scotland • Edinburgh Castle • street scenes • Princess Street • Scottish dancing performance • Loch Katrine • Loch Loman • unidentified Scottish town • street scenes • sign: "England & Norway"
    - Reversal original, 16mm, sound, color, 37.34 minutes (Box 1, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0006)
  - Norway, Sweden, Denmark, 1955, 7; 31.23 minutes
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 31.23 minutes (Box 1, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0007)
  - France, Italy, 1955, 8; 23 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0008 France, Italy, 1955 Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color 23:30 minutes
    • Eiffel Tower, as captured from a boat cruising the Seine • views of Paris from the Seine: bridges, buildings, other boats • Margolins and friends on boat • miniature Statue of Liberty • more shots of the Eiffel Tower • Notre Dame from the Seine • man with movie camera on the boat deck, filming • visit to Versailles, including gardens, exteriors, and some interior shots • sign: "Marie Antoinette" • roadway with directional sign: "Paris" • close-up on directional sign: "Paris" • street scenes • Arc de Triomphe, eternal flame and flowers • Obelisque de Luxor in the Place de la Concorde • street scenes, Place de la Concorde • Dorothy walks toward camera at Versailles? • Dorothy interacts with woman selling lace • gates of Versailles? • woman selling lace • Dorothy gets into car • Dorothy crosses street, stops and poses near uniformed man, pans to large building • Dorothy poses on narrow street, outside of Cinema Photo store • exteriors of Versailles and the grounds, including Dorothy and Morris • countryside, pond with water lilies • sidewalk cafe, Dorothy at table • Brasserie du Musee • bicyclist on narrow street • Dorothy walks across empty square • sign on awning: Café A Tout Va Bien Tabac, pans to street scenes • exteriors of unidentified church • street scenes, bicyclists, pedestrians crossing street • Dorothy walks on cobblestone street, café in background • Dorothy pretends to hitchhike next to sign: "N5 Fontainebleau 8 Paris 66" • exteriors of Fontainebleau, Dorothy walks toward palace • interiors of Fontainebleau, including close-ups on artworks; some too dark to see • view of Fontainebleau from cafe • woman wearing a hat approaches a horse on the street, pets it; others follow suit • street scenes, shot from above; pedestrians and traffic • long shot of Dorothy, walks toward camera; Miramar [Hotel] in background • Dorothy walks toward camera, ocean and rocks in the background • Dorothy skips back toward water • close-up on the Miramar [Hotel] • street scenes • close up: Jean Patou • traffic cop directs traffic • beach scenes • Kodak store in background, Dorothy nearby; pedestrians and traffic in foreground • Dorothy considers shop offerings • Dorothy walks toward camera, casino in background, pans over to La Maison Basque • Dorothy poses against fence, shops and ocean in background • Dorothy outside of Casino Bellevue, walks toward camera • street scenes • Dorothy passes small art gallery, Exposition Moreau; stops to show off the paintings • Dorothy at café table with huge tray of seafood • Dorothy walks by alley that looks onto ocean • uniformed man outside of building • Dorothy in hotel lobby or restaurant? • beach scenes, bikinis, includes shots of Dorothy • Dorothy goes for a swim • Necresco Hotel in Nice, France • street scenes • shots of cityscape across the water • cars parked along street near ocean, sign: "Frontière" • bumper to bumper traffic at Italian border • sign: "Arret obligatoire des vehicules allant en Italie" • street scenes, architecture • narrow Italian street • Dorothy wanders through crowded city square • tops of ornate buildings in Genova? • street scenes, architecture • Dorothy? stands next to large columns • sidewalk scenes • aerial views of city, Christopher Columbus statue? • aerial views of harbor, ocean, apartment buildings • aerial view of horse (or donkey?) drawn cart • ocean dotted with sailboats • sidewalk scene • two men gesture, point • pans to café tables and chairs on open street near small inlet filled with boats • Dorothy wanders around, interacts with the two men • one of the men points camera toward Morris's camera • three men stand around, discussing • Dorothy looks at fabric? being sold at a stand • boats rocking in the inlet • Dorothy walks along street; boats, buildings, water in the background • Dorothy poses with the two men by the water • Morris and Dorothy, holding hands, walk toward water; joined by one of the men, they shake hands and pose • scenic shots of water, buildings and hills • Dorothy and the two men sitting at café table • Dorothy climbs into a donkey drawn cart • the two men sit at the café table • Morris talks to someone on the steps of the Monte Carlo Casino • Morris shows empty pockets and walks down the stairs • exteriors of the Monte Carlo Casino • Dorothy waves from parking lot • view of the cityscape • Dorothy walks along, stopping across the street from the Carlton • large promenade near beach • beach scenes • people gather at tourist site? Dorothy in background • unidentified church, Dorothy on street below it • sign: "La Provence" • quiet city square • signs on awning: "Hotel de France / L'Auberge de France" • police officer? stands near row of cars • Dorothy sits at café, smokes a cigarette, waiter comes by • Dorothy walks out of L'Hotel de Paris et de la Poste in Sens, France • sign: "Boucherie Chevaline"
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 23:30 minutes (Box 1, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0008)
  - Spain, S.S. Queen Elizabeth, 1955, 9; 22.22 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0009 Spain, S.S. Queen Elizabeth, 1955 Reversal original, 16mm, sound, color 22.22 minutes